<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<resources>
    <string name="app_name">Art Space</string>

    <!-- Vincent van Gogh -->
    <string name="art_1_artist">Vincent van Gogh</string>
    <string name="art_1_artist_info">(Dutch, 1853 – 1890)</string>
    <string name="art_1_title">The Starry Night</string>
    <string name="art_1_year"> (1889)</string>
    <string name="art_1_description">The Starry Night by Vincent van Gogh</string>
    <string name="art_1_artist_bio">
        Vincent Willem van Gogh was a Dutch post-impressionist painter who posthumously became one of the most famous and influential figures in the history of Western art. In a decade, he created about 2,100 artworks, including around 860 oil paintings, most of which date from the last two years of his life. They include landscapes, still lifes, portraits, and self-portraits and are characterized by bold colors and dramatic, impulsive, and expressive brushwork that contributed to the foundations of modern art. He was not commercially successful, and his suicide at 37 came after years of mental illness, depression, and poverty.&#10;&#10;Born into an upper-middle-class family, Van Gogh drew as a child and was serious, quiet, and thoughtful. As a young man, he worked as an art dealer, often traveling, but became depressed after he was transferred to London. He turned to religion and spent time as a Protestant missionary in southern Belgium. He drifted into ill health and solitude before taking up painting in 1881, having moved back home with his parents. His younger brother Theo supported him financially, and the two kept a long correspondence by letter. His early works, mostly still lifes and depictions of peasant laborers, contain few signs of the vivid color that distinguished his later work. In 1886, he moved to Paris, where he met members of the avant-garde, including Émile Bernard and Paul Gauguin, who were reacting against the Impressionist sensibility. As his work developed, he created a new approach to still lifes and local landscapes. His paintings grew brighter in color as he developed a style that became fully realized during his stay in Arles in the south of France in 1888. During this period, he broadened his subject matter to include a series of olive trees, wheat fields, and sunflowers.&#10;&#10;Van Gogh suffered from psychotic episodes and delusions, and though he worried about his mental stability, he often neglected his physical health, did not eat properly, and drank heavily. His friendship with Gauguin ended after a confrontation with a razor when, in a rage, he severed part of his left ear. He spent time in psychiatric hospitals, including a period at Saint-Rémy. After he discharged himself and moved to the Auberge Ravoux in Auvers-sur-Oise near Paris, he came under the care of the homeopathic doctor Paul Gachet. His depression continued, and on 27 July 1890, Van Gogh shot himself in the chest with a Lefaucheux revolver. He died from his injuries two days later.&#10;&#10;Van Gogh was unsuccessful during his lifetime, and he was considered a madman and a failure. He became famous after his suicide and exists in the public imagination as a misunderstood genius, the artist "where discourses on madness and creativity converge." His reputation began to grow in the early 20th century as elements of his painting style came to be incorporated by the Fauves and German Expressionists. He attained widespread critical, commercial, and popular success over the ensuing decades, and he is remembered as an important but tragic painter whose troubled personality typifies the romantic ideal of the tortured artist. Today, Van Gogh\'s works are among the world\'s most expensive paintings to have ever sold, and his legacy is honored by a museum in his name, the Van Gogh Museum in Amsterdam, which holds the world\'s largest collection of his paintings and drawings.
    </string>

    <!-- Leonardo da Vinci -->
    <string name="art_2_artist">Leonardo da Vinci</string>
    <string name="art_2_artist_info">(Italian, 1452 – 1519)</string>
    <string name="art_2_title">The Mona Lisa</string>
    <string name="art_2_year"> (1503 – 1505)</string>
    <string name="art_2_description">The Mona Lisa by Leonardo da Vinci</string>
    <string name="art_2_artist_bio">
        Leonardo da Vinci was an Italian polymath of the High Renaissance who is widely considered one of the greatest painters of all time. The Mona Lisa is the most famous of his works and the most famous portrait ever made. The Last Supper is the most reproduced religious painting of all time, and his Vitruvian Man drawing is also regarded as a cultural icon. He is also known for his notebooks, in which he made drawings and notes on science and invention; these involve a variety of subjects, including anatomy, cartography, painting, and paleontology. Leonardo\'s collective works compose a contribution to later generations of artists rivaled only by that of his contemporary Michelangelo.&#10;&#10;Properly named Leonardo di ser Piero da Vinci, Leonardo was born out of wedlock to a notary, Piero da Vinci, and a peasant woman, Caterina, in Vinci, in the region of Florence, Italy. Leonardo was educated in the studio of the renowned Italian painter Andrea del Verrocchio. Much of his earlier working life was spent in the service of Ludovico il Moro in Milan, and he later worked in Rome, Bologna, and Venice. He spent his last three years in France, where he died in 1519.&#10;&#10;Although he had no formal academic training, many historians and scholars regard Leonardo as the prime exemplar of the "Renaissance Man" or "Universal Genius", an individual of "unquenchable curiosity" and "feverishly inventive imagination." He is widely considered one of the most diversely talented individuals ever to have lived. According to art historian Helen Gardner, the scope and depth of his interests were without precedent in recorded history, and "his mind and personality seem to us superhuman, while the man himself mysterious and remote." Scholars interpret his view of the world as being based on logic, though the empirical methods he used were unorthodox for his time.&#10;&#10;Leonardo is revered for his technological ingenuity. He conceptualized flying machines, a type of armored fighting vehicle, concentrated solar power, an adding machine, and the double hull. Relatively few of his designs were constructed or even feasible during his lifetime, as the modern scientific approaches to metallurgy and engineering were only in their infancy during the Renaissance. Some of his smaller inventions, however, entered the world of manufacturing unheralded, such as an automated bobbin winder and a machine for testing the tensile strength of wire. He is also sometimes credited with the inventions of the parachute, helicopter, and tank. He made substantial discoveries in anatomy, civil engineering, geology, optics, and hydrodynamics, but he did not publish his findings, and they had little to no direct influence on subsequent science.
    </string>

    <!-- Caspar David Friedrich -->
    <string name="art_3_artist">Caspar David Friedrich</string>
    <string name="art_3_artist_info">(German, 1774 – 1840)</string>
    <string name="art_3_title">Wanderer above the Sea of Fog</string>
    <string name="art_3_year"> (1818)</string>
    <string name="art_3_description">Wanderer above the Sea of Fog by Caspar David Friedrich</string>
    <string name="art_3_artist_bio">
        Caspar David Friedrich was a 19th-century German Romantic landscape painter, generally considered the most important German artist of his generation. He is best known for his mid-period allegorical landscapes, which typically feature contemplative figures silhouetted against night skies, morning mists, barren trees, or Gothic or megalithic ruins.&#10;&#10;His primary interest as an artist was the contemplation of nature, and his often symbolic and anti-classical work seeks to convey a subjective, emotional response to the natural world. Friedrich\'s paintings characteristically set a human presence in diminished perspective amid expansive landscapes, reducing the figures to a scale that, according to the art historian Christopher John Murray, directs "the viewer\'s gaze towards their metaphysical dimension."
    </string>

    <!-- Michelangelo -->
    <string name="art_4_artist">Michelangelo</string>
    <string name="art_4_artist_info">(Italian, 1475 – 1564)</string>
    <string name="art_4_title">Tondo Doni</string>
    <string name="art_4_year"> (1504 – 1506)</string>
    <string name="art_4_description">Tondo Doni by Michelangelo</string>
    <string name="art_4_artist_bio">
        Michelangelo di Lodovico Buonarroti Simoni, known as Michelangelo, was an Italian sculptor, painter, architect, and poet of the High Renaissance born in the Republic of Florence, who exerted an unparalleled influence on the development of Western art. His artistic versatility was of such a high order that he is often considered a contender for the title of the archetypal Renaissance man, along with his rival and elder contemporary, Leonardo da Vinci. Several scholars have described Michelangelo as the greatest artist of his age and even as the greatest artist of all time.&#10;&#10;A number of Michelangelo\'s works of painting, sculpture, and architecture rank among the most famous in existence. His output in these fields was prodigious; given the sheer volume of surviving correspondence, sketches, and reminiscences, he is the best-documented artist of the 16th century. He sculpted two of his best-known works, the Pietà and David, before the age of thirty. Despite holding a low opinion of painting, he also created two of the most influential frescoes in the history of Western art: the scenes from Genesis on the ceiling of the Sistine Chapel in Rome and The Last Judgment on its altar wall. His design of the Laurentian Library pioneered Mannerist architecture. At the age of 74, he succeeded Antonio da Sangallo the Younger as the architect of St. Peter\'s Basilica. He transformed the plan so that the western end was finished to his design, as was the dome, with some modifications after his death.&#10;&#10;Michelangelo was the first Western artist whose biography was published while he was alive. In fact, two biographies were published during his lifetime. One of them, by Giorgio Vasari, proposed that Michelangelo\'s work transcended that of any artist, living or dead, and was "supreme in not one art alone but in all three."&#10;&#10;In his lifetime, Michelangelo was often called Il Divino ("the divine one"). His contemporaries often admired his terribilità—his ability to instil a sense of awe. Attempts by subsequent artists to imitate Michelangelo\'s impassioned, highly personal style resulted in Mannerism, the next major movement in Western art after the High Renaissance.
    </string>

    <!-- Edvard Munch -->
    <string name="art_5_artist">Edvard Munch</string>
    <string name="art_5_artist_info">(Norwegian, 1863 – 1944)</string>
    <string name="art_5_title">The Scream</string>
    <string name="art_5_year"> (1893)</string>
    <string name="art_5_description">The Scream by Edvard Munch</string>
    <string name="art_5_artist_bio">
        Edvard Munch was a Norwegian painter. His best-known work, The Scream, has become one of the iconic images of world art.&#10;&#10;His childhood was overshadowed by illness, bereavement, and the dread of inheriting a mental condition that ran in the family. Studying at the Royal School of Art and Design in Kristiania (today\'s Oslo), Munch began to live a bohemian life under the influence of the nihilist Hans Jæger, who urged him to paint his own emotional and psychological state (\'soul painting\'). From this emerged his distinctive style.&#10;&#10;Travel brought new influences and outlets. In Paris, he learned much from Paul Gauguin, Vincent van Gogh and Henri de Toulouse-Lautrec, especially their use of colour. In Berlin, he met the Swedish dramatist August Strindberg, whom he painted, as he embarked on his major canon The Frieze of Life, depicting a series of deeply-felt themes such as love, anxiety, jealousy and betrayal, steeped in atmosphere.&#10;&#10;The Scream was conceived in Kristiania. According to Munch, he was out walking at sunset when he \'heard the enormous, infinite scream of nature.\' The painting\'s agonized face is widely identified with the angst of the modern person. Between 1893 and 1910, he made two painted versions and two in pastels, as well as a number of prints. One of the pastels would eventually command the fourth-highest nominal price paid for a painting at auction.&#10;&#10;As his fame and wealth grew, his emotional state remained insecure. He briefly considered marriage but could not commit himself. A breakdown in 1908 forced him to give up heavy drinking, and he was cheered by his increasing acceptance by the people of Kristiania and exposure to the city\'s museums. His later years were spent working in peace and privacy. Although his works were banned in Nazi Germany, most of them survived World War II, securing him a legacy.
    </string>

    <!-- Katsushika Hokusai -->
    <string name="art_6_artist">Katsushika Hokusai</string>
    <string name="art_6_artist_info">(Japanese, 1760 – 1849)</string>
    <string name="art_6_title">The Great Wave off Kanagawa</string>
    <string name="art_6_year"> (1831)</string>
    <string name="art_6_description">The Great Wave off Kanagawa by Katsushika Hokusai</string>
    <string name="art_6_artist_bio">
        Katsushika Hokusai, known simply as Hokusai, was a Japanese artist, ukiyo-e painter and printmaker of the Edo period. Born in Edo (now Tokyo), Hokusai is best known as author of the woodblock print series Thirty-six Views of Mount Fuji (富嶽三十六景, Fugaku Sanjūroku-kei, c. 1831) which includes the internationally iconic print, The Great Wave off Kanagawa.&#10;&#10;Hokusai created the Thirty-Six Views both as a response to a domestic travel boom and as part of a personal obsession with Mount Fuji. It was this series, specifically The Great Wave print and Fine Wind, Clear Morning, that secured Hokusai\'s fame both in Japan and overseas. As historian Richard Lane concludes, "if there is one work that made Hokusai\'s name, both in Japan and abroad, it must be this monumental print-series." While Hokusai\'s work prior to this series is certainly important, it was not until this series that he gained broad recognition.
    </string>
</resources>